<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei-scholia.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xd="http://www.oxygenxml.com/ns/doc/xsl">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Book 8 Scholia: Upsilon 1.1</title>
            <author>Stephanie Lindeborg</author>
            <author>Brian Clark</author>
            <author>Becky Musgrave</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Unpublished</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Transcribed directly from photography of E3 MS</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>

      <group n="8">

         <text n="e3">
            <body>


               <div n="2" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="10">Ι</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.1</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>This is the book they called the interrupted battle. For it being
                        problematic abbreviates the narrative of the Achaeans. Dawn is called
                        [yellow-veiled] <note resp="HMT">the word κεκροπεπλος cannot be read from
                           the text of the Upsilon 1.1 but is restored from an analogous scholion in
                           the Venetus B and the Iliadic line</note>, whenever there is much
                        darkness, there is some light. As opposed to [being called] <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">ροδοδακτυλος</foreign> (rosy-fingered). The periphrasis is
                        poetic. As [the poet] says day has come. εδκιδνατο is in the imperfect
                        tense, because the earth being spherical, is not illuminated all at once.
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>

               <div n="44" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="21">ΚΑ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.70</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>How does Zeus set down two fates/dooms as there is one fulfillment/end for
                        each army? In these matters they say that <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >πλειους</foreign> is a logical arrangement of words: <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">αἱ μὲν Ἀχαιῶν κῆρες</foreign> (The fates of the Achaeans).
                        Because there may be <foreign xml:lang="grc">δυο</foreign> (two) or <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">πολλαι</foreign> (many). Indeed I say that matters are
                        twofold. But others it is "πλειονων" with the noun giving emphasis.
                        Similarly in a change of case he [the poet] said <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >πλεονας</foreign>. It is a figure of speech, one of the measuring out
                        together figures of speech. Death is said to be like burning. Therefore one
                        is put to rest through fire. If it reveals/releases the soul as if it were .
                        For one customarily searches for knowledge in oneself. </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="7">Ζ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.33</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>He does not reveal his thoughts because he wishes to be an ally to the
                        Trojans. But he orders them to hinder themselves in aiding both sides. She,
                        understanding it, refuted his logic.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="68" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="20">Κ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.114</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>In the line he has shown that it is expected that he [Sthenelos] be left
                        behind. For he has not said previously where the charioteers were. They say
                        that Sthenelos having been brought down from the walls was wounded with
                        respect to his leg and because of this he did not fight but rather held the
                        reins for Diomedes.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="69" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="21">ΚΑ ΚΑ</num><note resp="HMT">There are two scholion numbers,
                           one written in the interior margin and one written before the scholion
                           text</note></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.112</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>It is economical for Nestor to mount the chariot of Diomedes, in order that
                        he be persuaded to flee and to yield to the exhortations of Nestor. For he
                        [Diomedes] could not be persuaded by Sthenelus. Whereas not in the lines
                        above, was he [able] to urge him to mount the chariot.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="58" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="12">ΙΒ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.93</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The epithet is used because of the retreat. For it is necessary for him to
                        be such a soldier. For he is a farmer [as is seen] from the passage in which
                        he knows well how to move the sickle in the grass and all the implements for
                        farming. He is a ship-steerer because he keeps the sail straight (Odyssey
                        10.32). A carpenter, from the good condition of the stones. And from the
                        skillful sawing of wood. A shipbuilder from the ship. A hunter from leading
                        the hunting packs and from the knowledge of the mountains. A seer from the
                        landing places. A cook from, as is necessary, roasting and cutting up. A
                        doctor, from the passages in which he diagnoses sickness and cuts out
                        arrows. A musician and a singer from beauty of his songs and speeches. A
                        boxer and a wrestler from versatility and his wrestling grip. An archer,
                        from the best ability to survey. A javelin-thrower, from the passage where
                        he throws the spear well. An orator, from his persuasiveness. A general from
                        his foresight and manly courage. A soldier from craftiness and great
                        experience</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="153" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="7">Ζ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.233</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Rather the full form <foreign xml:lang="grc">αντα</foreign>. As is
                        preferable to Herodian as well. Indeed it is not <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >αντι</foreign> even though it seemed so to Aristarchus.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="128" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="17">ΙΖ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.208</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>He does not say, as is common, <foreign xml:lang="grc">την δ’ ημειβετ’
                           επειτα</foreign>. But on account of her harshness, he renounces her
                        impudence.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="21">ΚΑ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.13</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Tartarus is opposite to Olympus. For the one, "never shook with winds, nor
                        with heavy rain" (Odyssey 6.43). And the other is chaotic and it seems to be
                        cold, from which they say that to fall into Tartarus is to be violently
                        cold. And the one is wholly shone upon and the other is cloudy</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="24">ΚΔ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.16</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The heavens, as he [the poet] says, have three distinct parts. The lower air
                        spans up to the clouds. Then the aether spans up to the visible places and
                        the realm of Zeus. And in a similar way so it goes from the earth to Hades,
                        from Hades to Tartarus. And so the earth is clearly as the middle center
                        point. And it is right to say that it is as far beneath the earth as the
                        earth is from heaven. And indeed perhaps he [the poet] calls it Hades
                        because of the rulership of Hades.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="127" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="16">ΙϚ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.206-8.207</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>One ought to place the nu at the beginning of the line because the consonant
                        is before the elision and is connected to the following vowel. But there is
                        a full stop after the nu. For it should be placed between the syllable and
                        between the elision. Often in the beginning of a line a full stop is placed
                        poetically. </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="180" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="21">ΚΑ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.261-8.266</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The poet, reporting the flight of the Greeks, does not require many names.
                        But now in the battle he recalls many of those who retreated.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="181" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="22">ΚΒ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.266</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The poet makes a distinction because he is about to speak about him
                        [Teucer]. But Odysseus is within rousing the soldiers. Thoas is also not
                        mentioned and he [Thoas] is not entirely cowardly [either]. <note resp="HMT"
                           >see Iliad 7.168</note></p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="57" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="11">ΙΑ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.92</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>In the lines, it is apparent that Odysseus has also fled. Above mention is
                        made of him, but Diomedes is always steadfast and he alone wishes to go
                        nowhere. </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="62" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="14">ΙΔ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.97</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>He did not hear because of the noise or he was not persuaded because of the
                        crisis. For he flees with the Ajaxes and he does not want to wage war
                        against the gods. For how is that cowardly? He is fleeing with everyone
                        else. Because Diomedes would not have called out to him alone.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="107" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="5">Ε</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.178</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>From the one <foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐδενόσωρα</foreign>. Because such a
                        compound also is rare. But I say it is [a compound] from the negation and
                        the conjunction [<foreign xml:lang="grc">δε</foreign>] and because of the
                        genitive <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἑνὸς</foreign> . But others preserve it as
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐδενὸς</foreign>. But it is persuasive to
                        remember that it is a recent work [i.e. the wall], when he [Hector] is
                        greatly disparaging the action of the Achaeans.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="283" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="12">ΙΒ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.408</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>"to hinder" but the metaphor is taken from spears being struck against
                        shields. </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="90" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="16">ΙϚ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.150</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>t is <foreign xml:lang="grc">εὐρεῖα</foreign> instead of <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">εὐρέως</foreign>, and he says that death is better than
                        disgrace.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="308" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="8">Η</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.429</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Whenever he [the poet] is looking at the reputation of the gods, then he
                        says they would not be moved by anything concerning mortals. Just as we
                        would not be moved concerning ants. But whenever he considers poetry, he
                        follows the stories and makes the subject famous: bringing about alliances
                        and wars among gods.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="390" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="5">Ε</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.526-8.527</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Look at the change of mind of Hector. He was speaking to his wife "The day
                        shall come when sacred Ilion is destroyed" (Iliad 6.448). But it is so
                        elsewhere. For there he is despondent because the Trojans were inferior. But
                        here he hopes for good fortune because they are superior in battle.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="92" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="18">ΙΗ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.153-8.154</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>First it is not clear if he [Hector] will say [what Diomedes thinks he
                        will], and otherwise he will not persuade them. But he [Nestor] assails to
                        the ones considering what men will say to them. Let them not care what sort
                        of thing it is.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="93" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="19">ΙΘ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.157</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Sensibly, he [Nestor] does not wait for the refutation of Diomedes, nor does
                        he force him, being a lover of honor, to agree to flee. But he turns the
                        horses so that the poet does not lessen Diomedes' honor because of these
                        things.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="100" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="24">ΚΔ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.167</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>How having said that Diomedes is divided into two minds, he [the poet] only
                        includes one. But we say that [he is] divided into two plans which converge
                        into one: "to turn the horses and be at war with the enemy." Or that he lets
                        go of the one which is said the same way, rather than to turn or not to
                        turn, which he [the poet] leaves one out.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="264" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="7">Ζ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.377-8.378</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Expressively and this regarding the [line] "one who rages beyond what can be
                        endured" (Iliad 8.355). Aristarchus writes <foreign xml:lang="grc">προφανεῖα</foreign> in the dual. But
                        Herodian would rather <foreign xml:lang="grc">προφανείσας</foreign> contracting the alpha in the Doric
                        dialect, by which we are also persuaded. </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="232" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="10">Ι</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.349</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Aristarchus says <foreign xml:lang="grc">οἴματα</foreign> but the others say
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὄμματα</foreign>. Because he says <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">βλοσσυρῶπις</foreign>. He [the poet] is accustomed to
                        characterize the face from the eyes. For example "possessing the eyes of a
                        dog" (Iliad 1.225). But Aristarchus writes <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >γοργόνος</foreign> wrongly. For neither the poet nor Hesiod say <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">γοργὼν</foreign> but rather <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >γοργώ</foreign>.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="204" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="11">ΙΑ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.296</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>This says <foreign xml:lang="grc">εἰρωνευόμενος</foreign> instead of
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">δεξιούμενος</foreign> and
                           <foreign>φιλοφρονούμενος</foreign>. For it is clear it is <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">δεδεγμένος</foreign> from <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >δέχεσθαι</foreign>.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="376" type="scholion">
                  <div type="marker">
                     <p><num value="16">ΙϚ</num></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.e3:8.513</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The wound from the missile. As in <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὡς δ’ ὅτ’ ἂν
                           ὠδίνουσαν ἔχῃ βέλος</foreign> "Just as when the missile grabs hold of a
                        woman in labor" (Iliad 11.269).</p>
                  </div>
               </div>

            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
