<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="../css/tei-scholia.css"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xd="http://www.oxygenxml.com/ns/doc/xsl">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Book 8 Scholia: Venetus A</title>
            <author>Stephanie Lindeborg</author>
            <author>Brian Clark</author>
            <author>Becky Musgrave</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Unpublished</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Transcribed directly from photography of Venetus A MS</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>

      <group n="8">
         <text n="msAim">
            <body>
               <div n="213" type="scholion">
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.304</p>
                     <div type="comment">
                        <p>Aristarchus writes <foreign xml:lang="grc">Αἱσύμνηθεν</foreign> as does
                           the text of Zenodtus and the text of Aristophanes.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="124" type="scholion">
                  <div type="reference">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.157</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The texts of Aristarchus have it this way <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >τραπε</foreign> with the alpha. </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="200" type="scholion">
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.290</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Zenodotus, Aristophanes, and those who agree with them [write] <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">ἵππω</foreign>.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="246" type="scholion">
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.371</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The lines were not in Zendotous.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text n="msAint">
            <body>
               <div n="128" type="scholion">
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.166</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>In Zendotos [it is] <foreign xml:lang="grc">ποτμον ἐφήσω</foreign>.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text n="msA">
            <body>
               <div n="6" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p/>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.12</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Since heaven has three distinct parts: the lower air spans up until the
                        clouds, then the aether spans up until the visible places. In a similar way
                        so it goes both from earth to Hades and from Hades to Tartarus, Tartarus is
                        in opposition to Olympus. For the one, “never shook with winds, nor with
                        heavy rain” (Odyssey 6.43). And the other seemed to be both chaotic and
                        cold, indeed they say that to fall into Tartarus is to be violently cold.
                        The former is wholly shone upon. The latter is murky.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>

               <div n="12" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>So much below Hades:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.16</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>This is the arrangement of the cosmos according to Homer. And because
                        nothing like this is said about Olympus, and because he leaves out υπερθεν,
                        which means as far as it is above.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>Tartarus:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.13</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The shadowy place below the earth, it is the bottommost portion of Hades.
                        And he says that it lies in the deepest region or that it is difficult and
                        vexatious. And it is so named because of the drawing out and the confounding
                        of everything in itself. But others understand it as the unlit region of
                        their inhabitance</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>All the way down to Hades:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.16</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>He says that Tartarus stands as far from Hades as Ouranus is from the earth.
                        And through these [references] he makes the cosmos spherical; he has
                        introduced the earth in the relation of the center [of the cosmos], he says
                        that [going] straight from the earth to each opposite side is
                        equidistant.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>Dawn:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.1</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>It means many things. On the one hand it is the part of day that has that
                        time. One the other hand it is the embodiment of a deity as it is in "Dawn
                        from her couch, next to noble Tithonos" (Iliad 11.1). The time from sunrise
                        until midday is the interval just as in "Twelve dawns have already passed
                        for me in Ilium" (Iliad 21.80-21.81).</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="78" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p/>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.93</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The epithet is for the retreat. 1. He is a farmer "in the grass, a curved
                        scythe" (Odyssey 18.368) 2. A steersman "for [I] always [steered] the sails
                        of the ship" (Odyssey 10.32) 3. A carpenter from the bed (cf. Odyssey
                        23.189) 4. A ship builder, from the raft (cf. Odyssey 5.243-5.261) 5. A
                        hunter, from [the hunt] at Parnassos (c.f. Odyssey 19.428-19.454) 6. A seer,
                        "I say let someone speak to me" (Odyssey 20.100) <note resp="HMT">Allen’s OCT edition of the
                        Odyssey reads φήμην τίς μοι φάσθω on this line instead of φημι τίς μοι
                        φάσθω, which would make it “let someone utter an omen to me”</note> 7. A cook
                        "cutting up and roasting" (Odyssey 15.323) 8. A doctor "so that he might
                        have to rub on his arrows" (Odyssey 1.262-263) 9. A musician "a speech like
                        a singer" (Odyssey 11.368) 10. A boxer "in boxing I overcame Klytomedes"
                        (Iliad 23.634) 11. A wrestler "in wrestling [I beat] Ancaeus of Pleuron"
                        (Iliad 23.635) 12. A discus thrower against the Phaiacians (cf. Odyssey
                        8.186-8.198) 13. An archer "I know the bow well" (Odyssey 8.215) 14. A
                        javelin-thrower "throwing a spear" (Odyssey 8.229) 15. An orator and an
                        astronomer "looking upon the Pleiades" (Odyssey 5.272)”</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="131" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>to turn the horses around</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.168</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>the sign is there because it is in the subjunctive. "Neither to retreat nor
                        to fight the enemy." But that is not so. For he was "of two minds." It was
                        not that he was worried about two different things, but that we interpret it
                        the same "to turn his horses and fight."</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="140" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>The shield of Nestor:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.192</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>It is symbolic of Nestor himself. For some say that his arms were wrought by
                        Hephaestus.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="146" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>the rods</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.193</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The bars with which one strengthens shields, for when they are attached to
                        the handle of a shield, which they call <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >οχανα</foreign>. For later these men had thought it came from the
                        Carians because Anacreon wrote "Carian-made shield bars."</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="147" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>embellished</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.195</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The sign is there because the arms are wrought by Hephaestus because he took
                        them from Glaukos and he handed out from the arms to his men, and it is not
                        in figurative language.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="167" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>Facing a hundred Trojans:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.233-8.234</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>There is an acute accent on the syllable <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >ανθ</foreign> because it is the full form <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >αντα</foreign> as Demetrios of Gonypesus correctly thought. And on my
                        part, this way of literary interpretation is acceptable. For clearly each
                        man says that he would make a stand against 100 or even 200 Trojans. For the
                        syntax of <foreign xml:lang="grc">αντα</foreign> is not delayed, unless it
                        takes the genitive. </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="153" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p/>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.213</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p><note resp="HMT">there is no critical sign on this line</note>The sign is
                        also there because <foreign xml:lang="grc">απο ταφρου πυργος εεργε</foreign>
                        is written in some sources. <foreign xml:lang="grc">εκ νεων</foreign> can be
                        connected with <foreign xml:lang="grc">απο ταφρου</foreign> because either
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">πυργος</foreign> (tower) or <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">ταφρος</foreign> (trench) can be against the ships. And it
                        is possible the things said between the wall the wall and trench, the most
                        of horses and men are between the wall and the trench, and when he says
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">εκ νεων</foreign> so that it it indicates the
                        space is left between the wall and the trench according to the topography of
                        newly built things/</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="222" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>drawing back</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.325</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The sign is there because <foreign xml:lang="grc">αυερυοντα</foreign> is
                        clearly means drawing backwards <note resp="HMT">if it's οπισω, there are
                           some issues in interpreting the words in the Byzantinue
                           orthography</note> and "a bow that's curved back" comes from this. One
                        must not entirely make a distinction for <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >αυερυοντα</foreign> as Neoteles thinks. For <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >ωμον</foreign> agrees with him [Teucer] both being hit and drawing.
                        Indeed, Neoteles of Scythia claims that archery is drawing the bow to the
                        shoulder.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="182" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>Teucer was ninth</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.266</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The sign is there because while everyone turned around, Odysseus alone
                        remained next to the ships with the result that the above line is in good
                        order "as he spoke he did not listen" (Iliad 8.97) because he voluntarily
                        sent himself past</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="197" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>Heracles: <note resp="HMT">this lemma is not actually from the
                        line</note></p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.284</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Heracles laid waste to windy Ilium and he took captive the daughter of
                        Laomedon and sister of Priam and gave her as a gift to Telemon since he
                        joined him on the expedition. From her, Telamon had Teucer. Since he brought
                        into the world by a Trojan woman, he called the child Teucer, moving the
                        accent back and making it a proper noun. For the Trojans were called the
                        Teucrians from their king Teucer. The story is more precisely told by many
                        others and by Apollonius the grammarian in the second generation. It is
                        asked how having received praise from everyone Teucer is now a bastard. We
                        say that it was not a cause for dishonor. Because the custom of the ancients
                        prevails. For they honored bastards equally with legitimate children. And
                        otherwise if someone was a spearman or a commoner but also a royal. And on
                        account of the magnification, we say that this is said for excellence that
                        he surpasses the legitimate children.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>golden rope:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.19</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The sign is there because if Olympus was not taken to be the mountain in
                        Macedon, it would not agree with these things. For he [the poet] says that
                        the drops of heaven draw Olympus up to a point so that a point may be bound
                        up form the peak and the sign is also there because the <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">εξ</foreign> is superfluous. </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="238" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>Gate-fastener:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.367</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>the gates are strongly bound together and closed because nothing returns
                        from Hades.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="239" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>bringing forth from Erebus the hound of loathed Hades:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.368</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The sign is there because he makes mention of only this Labor [of Herakles],
                        there are some according to legend. And because he calls him only <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">κυνα</foreign> and does not call him Cerberus as the newer
                        [poets] do. From the the greatest labor, he makes clear all of the labors.
                        They know the hound or the form of him. Pindar says he has 100 heads. And
                        Hesiod says he had 50 heads.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p/>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.29</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p><foreign xml:lang="grc">φρασσάμενοι</foreign> (pointing out) is written, but
                        rather <foreign xml:lang="grc">αγασσαμενοι</foreign> (wondering), is more in
                        accordance with what follows. </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="133" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>without strength</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.178</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Heraclides of Meilesius writes it with a grave accent/without an accent
                           <note resp="HMT">could mean either</note>, like <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >ἄσητα</foreign>, and he uses this word as though it is a stronger
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">βληξχρον</foreign>, it ought to mean "not weak"
                        like <foreign xml:lang="grc">ακακος</foreign> means “not evil", but it means
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀσθενές</foreign> (without strength). Indeed the
                        grammatical tradition marks it with an acute accent. <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >ἀβληχρὰ</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀβληχρὴν</foreign>
                        prevailed first by declining as if it is uncompounded. For thus they are
                        declined like <foreign xml:lang="grc">πενιχρα</foreign> and <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">ψυχρα</foreign>. And I write in the feminine just like
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀβληχρά</foreign> not sharing in whichever
                        gender. And I write <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὁ αβληχρὸς</foreign> and
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἡ ἀβληχρος</foreign>. Elsewhere already this
                        means <foreign xml:lang="grc">βληχρὸς</foreign>. Since after the majority
                        rather [the meaning] <foreign xml:lang="grc">ασθενες</foreign> (without
                        strength) Alcaeus 8 <foreign xml:lang="grc">βληχρῶν ἀνέμων ἀχείμαντοι
                           πνοαί</foreign> "not stormy blasts of weak wind." And Nicandros writes
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">βληχρὸν γὰρ μυὸς οἷα μυληβόρου ἐν χροῒ
                           νύγμα</foreign> "for the weakness of the mouse was a sort of
                        millstone-eating, like pricking on the skin." Indeed adding the alpha to it
                        keeps the accent in the same place. Because I know that the accent is always
                        the same in <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἄβορος</foreign>
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἄγαυρος</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >ἄσταχυς</foreign>.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="291" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>Indeed Dawn:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.470</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The sign is there because Zendotos writes <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἄας δη καὶ
                           μᾶλλον</foreign> instead of <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐσαύριον</foreign>
                        but the word is not Homeric</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="320" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>grain from your halls:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.505-8.507</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p><foreign xml:lang="grc">αξεσαι</foreign> is not the common form with
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">σιτου</foreign>, because inanimate objects do not
                        use the verb <foreign xml:lang="grc">αγω</foreign>, rather <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">φερεται</foreign>. Therefore <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >φερεται</foreign> must be understood as left out. </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="137" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>before you:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.188-8.190</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>This is the appropriate line order in my opinion <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἠ
                           εμοὶ ὅς πέρ οἱ θαλερὸς πόσις εὔχομαι εἶναι</foreign> then <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">οἴνον τ' ἐγκεράσασα πιεῖν ὅτε</foreign> μοι <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">θυμὸς ἀνώγοι</foreign> but one must see that before being
                        able to make use of the drinking cups they mix the drink</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="261" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>For she is always given to hinder me in whatever I have decreed:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.408</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐνικλᾶν</foreign> means "to hinder." It is a
                        metaphor from spears clashing against shields. And it must be written like
                        so: <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὅττι κεν εἴπω</foreign> only to hinder and not
                        to permit what is said by me. Again it is later written in the lines [that]
                        Iris says <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὅττι κεν εἴπῃ</foreign> (Iliad 8.422)</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="324" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>and the speech which:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.524-8.525</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The two lines are athetized. because the poet says nothing in the following
                        line. And he substitutes/uses the relative pronoun <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >ὃς μὲν</foreign> instead of the definite article <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >ὁ μέν</foreign>. But the intention is of this sort concerning the things
                        now and today, the reason is of service to me and nothing is omitted and
                        nothing is omitted concerning the things happening tomorrow which under dawn
                        I reveal.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="117" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>So shall he someday boast:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.150</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The sign is there because in general he [the poet] does not say <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">εὑρεῖαν</foreign>, but in my opinion the earth becomes
                        εὑρεῖα before he would compose <foreign xml:lang="grc">εὐρὺ
                        χάσμα</foreign></p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="80" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>may a man fleeing not:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.95</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Some make a distinction after the <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                        >φεύγοντι</foreign>, but let us also join the whole line. We know that a
                        man's back does not flee.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="132" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>giving a sign to the Trojans:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.171</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>One ought to have some short pause after <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >Τρώεσσιν</foreign>. Because the sign itself indicates the signal for the
                        subsequent victory. But if we join it together, it is incorrect syntax.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="208" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>but Archeptolemus</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.312</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The sign is there because Zenodotus left out <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >Ἀρχεπτόλεμον</foreign> and had composed above <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >Ἰ̈φιτίδην Ερασιπτόλεμον</foreign></p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="136" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>Xanthus and you Podargus and Aethon and goodly Lampus:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.185</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The sign is there because nowhere else does Homer show the use of four
                        horses yoked together. And it is also a discrepancy with the two being
                        brought forward and the simple address. There ought to be a short stop after
                        each name, but if the cold one is joined, it is not able to be understood,
                        because there are two epithets and two proper names, when the conjunctions
                        joined by juxtaposition separate themselves from each other, but the proper
                        names are never joined to the epithets.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="9011" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p/>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.206-8.207</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>But if it lay out of the full line, nothing would be questioned, but since
                        it is understood the nu in the next line and is carried over by the
                        grammarians, two rational follow. One because a period has fallen in the
                        middle of the syllable <foreign xml:lang="grc">ναυ</foreign> and it
                        possesses an interval of time, just like in the following: <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">ὡς ἔφαθ' αι δ' ἐπέμυξαν</foreign> (Iliad 4.20). <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">ὡς εφαθ’ οὐδ' ἀπίθησεν</foreign> (Iliad 2.166). The other
                        reason is because it comes together at the beginning of the line after only
                        the letter nu there is an interval of punctuation.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="154" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>all the way from the ships:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.213</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>There ought to be a short pause after the <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >νηων</foreign>, because it makes the idea expressed in <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">ὅσον</foreign> more clear. The trench is set away from the
                        walls and the ships, the multitude was composed of footsoldiers and horses,
                        leaving out the conjunction <foreign xml:lang="grc">και</foreign>. Because
                        the <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἔεργεν</foreign> indicates a separation between
                        the ships and the walls. The empty space in between was for a passage way.
                        The space was broad and wide in the beginning, and long through the whole
                        stream to the end. But again in this way, outside of the walls there was a
                        short gap, after which the trench was dug which that gap was of such a size
                        of one missile and the things on it are thrown from the ones attacking it.
                        Indeed there were spaces on each side of the walls: One filled up the space
                        before the trench, and the other before the ships. Nicanor says
                        likewise.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="180" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>diviner:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.250</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The sign is there because <foreign xml:lang="grc">πανομφαιος</foreign>
                        (diviner) <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὁ κληδωνιος</foreign> (receiver of omens)
                        and <foreign xml:lang="grc">πάσης κληδῶνος παραίτιος</foreign> (the causer
                        of all received omens) are not generally an epithet and because the epithet
                        here is a hapax. </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="183" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>he would peer around:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.269-8.270</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>There ought to be a short pause after <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >παπτηνας</foreign>. But it ought to be punctuated on the
                        corresponding/answering <foreign xml:lang="grc">βεβληκει</foreign>.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="241" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>She kissed his knees:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.371-8.372</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The two lines are athetized because it is not necessary to describe in
                        detail piece by piece the things to the one who already knows it well. And
                        indeed we do not narrate further something superfluous.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="236" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>tolerably:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.355</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Like <foreign xml:lang="grc">ανδρικως</foreign> Aristarchus pronounces it
                        with a circumflex, but it is said by us, regarding pronunciation, because we
                        make a distinction regarding the [the use of the word in] <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">ῆ δὴ λοίγια ἔργα τάδ' ἔσσεται οὐκέτ' ἀνεκτά</foreign>
                        (Iliad 1.573) </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="250" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>Let fall her soft robe:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.385-8.387</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The three are athetized because during the aristea of Diomedes it is well
                        brought out to completion. Because she does something. But here for no
                        reason she puts on her armor. But Aristophanes also athetizes them, and
                        Zenodotus does not write them.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="271" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>against the wall, shining</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.435</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>There ought to be a short pause after the <foreign xml:lang="grc">προς
                           ενώπια</foreign> so that the chariots are brightly shining. but one must
                        see that <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἅρματα</foreign> means the chariots
                           (<foreign xml:lang="grc">οχηματα</foreign>). </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="275" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>beneath a cloth:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.441</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>After it is formed thence it is accented with a grave. Since each accusative
                        singular ending in alpha is accented with a grave with something unmodified
                        having been removed, because of the well-ordered double nature and things of
                        this sort. But below he is covering and concealing with a simple cover.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="269" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>Let one of them perish:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.429</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Whenever he [the poet] is looking at the reputation of the gods, then he
                        says they would not be moved by anything concerning mortals. Just as we
                        would not be moved concerning ants. But whenever he considers poetry, he
                        follows the stories and makes the subject famous: bringing about alliances
                        and wars among gods.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="293" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>in the grimmest stress:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.475-8.476</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The two lines are athetized because through <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἥματι
                           τῷ</foreign> it indicates a postponement of more time, but in the
                        following lines, he brings forward Achilles to the ditch and he stands up to
                        argue precisely not when he will stand up for some most opportune moment.
                        But he holds off "until the swift footed son of Peleus is risen up next to
                        the ships" (Il. 8.474). And he holds some imposed falsehood, not because
                        they fight in great distress. But he is accustomed to say <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">στείνει</foreign> for a narrow road. But it is called a
                        confined space by most people. But he says <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >αινωτατω</foreign> for a place that is difficult because of fear.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="311" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>Hector:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.493</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The sign is there because Zenodotus rejects from these lines down to the
                        following four, because they are both written in another place. But
                        Aristarchus says that they remain more appropriately here because of the
                        discussion in the expedition.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="325" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>I pray having hoped:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.526</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The sign is there because Zenodotus writes <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἔλπομαι
                           εὐχόμενος</foreign>. He does not say Hector is lifted up thusly, I feel
                        hope praying to the gods. Because the opposite is suitable and appropriate,
                        "I pray, feeling hope." I speak aloud being made hopeful by Zeus and the
                        other gods.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="340" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>Tomorrow, which [will see] his excellence: </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.535-8.537</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The sign is there because it is necessary to keep these three lines, on
                        which he places an anti sigma. Or the following three, on which the stigma
                        are placed. Because they explain what the meaning is. But Aristarchus rather
                        accepts as genuine the second three because the words are more loudly
                        boastful. But Zenodotus accepts as genuine the first three and he does not
                        write the second three. But regarding these lines Didymus says the same
                        things, as does Aristonicus, for which reasons we did not write the things
                        of Didymus.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="81" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>So he spoke, but he did not hear/listen:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.97</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Regarding the ambiguity, whether he [Odysseus] did not generally perceive
                        his [Diomedes’] voice on account of clamor, or having heard him he passed
                        along, which is how Aristarchus takes it.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="82" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>He did not hear/listen,</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.97</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐδὲ ἤκουσεν</foreign> It is interpreted whether he
                        [Odysseus] generally did perceive his [Diomedes’] voice on account of
                        clamor, or having heard him he passed along, which is how Aristarchus takes
                        it</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="83" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>He did not hear/listen</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.97</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p><foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐδὲ ἤκουσεν</foreign> It is interpreted whether
                        Odysseus did not wholly hear, or whether he was not persuaded. They charge
                        the hero with cowardice, ignoring the <foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐδ’ ἐσάκουσεν</foreign>. For it is not “not
                        listening.” But rather it is a lack of perfect perception, and because he is
                        not a coward since he flees last of all the other men and because of his
                        slowness he is a specimen of a man who loves danger.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="152" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>The trench encloses the space all the way from the ships to the tower:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.213</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p> The Aristarcheans have it two ways: <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἔεργε</foreign>
                        and <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἔρυκε</foreign>. And it on both sides indicated
                        is such of the Achaeans, the trench divides all the way from the wall and is
                        full equally with horses and men driven together and shut in together by
                        Hector. Zenodotus writes <note resp="HMT">The scribe has accidentally
                           repeated a large portion of the text. The repeated text has been left out
                           of the translation for clarity.</note>
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">τῶν δ’ ὅσων ἐν νηῶν καὶ πύργου</foreign> (all the
                        way to the ships and the tower). But some say that the two spaces are full
                        of Greeks and from the ships until the wall and from the wall until the
                        ditch, which indeed he calls a narrow space (<foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >στεῖνος</foreign>). </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="233" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>Having the eyes of the Gorgon:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.349</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Zenodotus writes <foreign xml:lang="grc">Γοργονος ὄμματ’ ἔχων ἠὲ βροτολοιγοῦ
                           Ἄρηος</foreign> but Homer writes it without the nu <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">τῇ δ ἐπο μὲν Γοργῷ</foreign> (Il. 11.36) like <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">Σαπφώ</foreign>. On which account he writes <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">Γοργοῦς</foreign> like <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >Σαπφοῦς</foreign>. But Aristarchus writes it with the iota <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">οἴμματ’ ἔχων</foreign> and they say beside the path they
                        become roads and impulses. However, most texts have the demotic version:
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">Γοργοῦς ὅμματ’ ἔχων</foreign> which should be
                        understood also with what is said elsewhere namely: <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >τῇ δ’ ἐπι μὲν Γοργος βλωσυρωτης</foreign> (Il. 11.36) Indeed it is
                        difficult to say something certain. </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="248" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>He shinning will rejoice:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.378</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Aristarchus has <foreign xml:lang="grc">προφανέντες</foreign> similar to
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">πληγέντε κεραυνῷ</foreign> in the dual. But
                        Zenodotus has <foreign xml:lang="grc">γηθήσει προφανεῖσας ἰδὼν ἐς δοῦπον
                           ἀκόντων</foreign> contracting the ending with an acute accent on the
                        penult pronouncing with the alpha extended. And it is pure Dorian and a
                        rarity in something of this sort in the works of the poet.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="169" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>Hector who soon:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.235</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>They say that Aristarchus would be less reproachful [of this line], if
                        indeed it had been written as follows: <foreign xml:lang="grc">Εκτορος ὃ δὴ
                           κῦδος Ὀλύμπιος αὐτὸς ὀπάζει</foreign>. But it has been athetized also in
                        the text of Aristophanes. </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="199" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>From that moment waiting with bows:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.296</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Thus the Aristarcheans have <foreign xml:lang="grc">δεδεγμένος</foreign>
                        with a gamma. The Herodians have <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >δεδεχμένος</foreign> with a chi. And Diogenes says in the commentaries,
                        that he writes <foreign xml:lang="grc">εἰρωνευόμενος</foreign> something
                        like <foreign xml:lang="grc">δεξιούμενος τοῖς τόξοις</foreign>. Because
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">δεδέχεσθαι</foreign> is to welcome not without
                        charm or explanation.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="274" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>The chariot on a stand:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.441</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Chrysippus pronounces it as one word. Yet Aristarchus has it as two parts of
                        speech and accents it with a circumflex on the penult. Indeed he writes it
                        elsewhere as <foreign xml:lang="grc">χρύσειοι δ’ ἄρα κοῦροι ἐϋδμήτων ἐπι
                           βωμῶν</foreign> (Od. 7.100). Indeed it is necessary to recognize that it
                        is written with a mu. As it is similarly separated into two words in
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀμ φόνον ᾶν νέκυας</foreign> (Il. 10.298). And
                        the reason is explained in the Treatises Regarding Orthography
                        (2.408.20).</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="321" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>But so that some certain missile:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.513</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The sign is there because he said the weapon to indicate the wound, it being
                        a homonym for wounding. The texts of Aristophanes have <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">πέσσοι</foreign>. And Parmeniscus in Book One of Regarding
                        Dominance, like the Aristarchean text, has <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀλλ ὥς
                           τις κείνων γε</foreign></p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="326" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>Urged on the Fates:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.527</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>Aristarchus read it well as a compound, and the majority likewise also when
                        he resolves it into its elements it: <foreign xml:lang="grc">οὒς κῆρες
                           φορέουσιν</foreign> (Il. 8.528). Because it is customary for him to
                        resolve the compound often. But never lengthening out the syllable in the
                        dative, at the beginning it is compounded like <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >πασι</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">πάντεσσι</foreign> in
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">παειμέλουσα</foreign> (Od. 12.70). The compound
                        is not only derived from from <foreign xml:lang="grc">πάντεσσι</foreign>,
                        [for example] <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ναυσικάα</foreign>
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ναυσίθοος</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                           >ἐγχεσίμοροι</foreign>
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">τειχεσιπλήτης</foreign>. I placed it at the
                        beginning, according to the [argument] from Epicharmos, and I compound it at
                        the end like <foreign xml:lang="grc">γυναικ’ ἄνδρεσσι ποθεινοί</foreign>.
                        Indeed if that is true it is clear that is is contrary to the rule. The
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">κηρεσσιφορήτους</foreign> must be read as a
                        compound, but nevertheless the Aristarchean text is the authority
                        according which logic we say it.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="227" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>Hector among the frontlines:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.337</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The texts of Aristarchus have it without the nu and it is: <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">Ἕκτωρ δὲ πρώτοισι</foreign>. Hector was hastening on at
                        the front lines.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="259" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>They shall thoroughly heal the wounds:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.405</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>In the other [text] of Aristarchus it is <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἕλκε
                           ἀπαλθήσονται</foreign> and there never is the superior form: <foreign
                           xml:lang="grc">ἕλκη ἀπαλθήσονται</foreign>. </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="47" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>smaller:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.56</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The sign is there because he [the poet] always says the Trojans with their
                        allies are a smaller group. And the repetition with respect to those
                        athetized lines, for example <foreign xml:lang="grc">πολλεων ἐκ πολίων
                           ἐχξέσπαλοι ἄνδρες</foreign> (Il. 2.131) and the things written in
                        Zenodotus <foreign xml:lang="grc">μυρία δ’ ἐν πεδίω</foreign>.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="196" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>and indeed you being a bastard:</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.284</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>In Zenodotos, the line was not there. And it is athetized in Aristophanes
                        because the family history is inappropriate and does not suit an exhortation
                        but rather is a reproach and a dissuasion [from action]. </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="346" type="scholion">
                  <div type="lemma">
                     <p>From which everything is seen: </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="ref">
                     <p>urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg001.msA:8.557</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="comment">
                     <p>The line is athetized because it is rather similar to the looking down on
                        Patroclus. And what follows is athetized along with it because he wishes to
                        stand there suddenly illuminated, so that Patroclus may be viewed suddenly.
                        But there the stillness is stretched out for tranquility. It is not
                        transmitted in Zenodotus's text. And Aristophanes also athetized it.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>

            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
